Mary Jo Weaver papers, 1972-2010 C371
Indiana University Archives
Mary Jo Weaver papers
1972-2010
1975-2006
Indiana University Archives
Weaver, Mary Jo
C371
4 cubic feet
Mary Jo Weaver served as a professor in the Department of Religious Studies at Indiana University from 1975 until her retirement in 2006. Her teaching career, scholarly activities, professional service, and publications are represented in the contents of this collection.
Access Restrictions
The Promotion and Tenure file is closed to researchers at this time.
Advance notice is required for access to the collection.
Biographical Note
Born on December 16, 1942, Mary Jo Weaver began her scholastic career by obtaining a Bachelor's Degree in Chemistry from Ohio Dominican College in 1964. She then went on to receive a Master's Degree in Theology from the University of Notre Dame in 1968 before becoming the first lay woman to receive a PhD in Theology from Notre Dame with her 1973 dissertation, "Pneuma in Philo of Alexandria." During this time, Dr. Weaver also served as an Assistant Professor of Religious Studies at Pontifical College Josephinum in Columbus, Ohio, from 1972 to 1975.
Dr. Weaver's teaching career within the Indiana University Department of Religious Studies spanned the period from 1975 until her retirement in 2006. She now holds the title of Professor Emerita. In addition to teaching, she also served in a variety of administrative roles both within the University and in a number of professional organizations as well.
Throughout her career, Dr. Weaver has been actively involved in research and publishing on subjects relating to American Catholicism, contemporary Christianity, women and religion, and mysticism and spirituality. These research interests are also reflected in the classes she taught at IU, most notably in her courses "American Catholicism," "Introduction to Christianity," "Women and Religion," and "Star Trek and Religion."
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series: Biographical records, Publications and writings, Presentations, Teaching materials, Audio/Visual materials, and Research notes, grants, and correspondence. The Publications and writings series is further organized into three subseries: Monographs, Articles, and Miscellaneous writings.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials ranging from 1972 to 2010 that document the career of Mary Jo Weaver, a Professor in the Department of Religious Studies at Indiana University. This collection is divided into six series: Biographical records, Publications and writings, Presentations, Teaching materials, Audio/Visual materials, and Research notes, grants, and correspondence.
The first series, Biographical records, is arranged alphabetically and contains materials from 1973 to 2008. This series is comprised of materials that document Dr. Weaver's teaching, research, and professional activities throughout her career, including faculty summary reports for the classes she taught at IU, her degree from the University of Notre Dame, awards she won, statements about her work written both autobiographically by her and by others, and correspondence, a scrapbook, and a certificate related to her retirement from teaching at IU.
The Publications and writings series is arranged chronologically and spans the period from 1972 to 2010. It is further organized into three subseries: Monographs, Articles, and Miscellaneous writings. The Monographs subseries contains books and chapters of books written by or edited by Dr. Weaver. The Articles subseries contains articles written by Dr. Weaver that appeared in scholarly journals and religious publications. The Miscellaneous writings subseries contains Dr. Weaver's doctoral dissertation, in addition to editorials, pamphlets, and reviews written by Weaver, as well as reviews written about her publications.
The Presentations series is arranged chronologically and contains copies of lectures and sermons given by Dr. Weaver from 1974 to 2001. These presentations were given at churches, professional conferences, and at other universities, and often featured topics exploring liberal and conservative Catholic viewpoints as well as the relationship of women and the Church.
The Teaching materials series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the class and contains items from courses taught by Dr. Weaver from the 1970s to 2005 at IU and the Pontifical Josephinum, as well as adult education classes early in her career. These materials are comprised of syllabi, reading lists, exams, and lectures and lecture notes. Of note in this series are the three folders of materials related to Dr. Weaver's course on Star Trek and Religion.
The Audio/Visual materials series is a chronologically arranged collection of cassette tape recordings of Dr. Weaver's radio appearances and conference presentations from 1983 to 1996, as well as a VHS tape recording of Dr. Weaver from 1995 (stored separately; consult Archives staff for details). The audio tapes within this series include Dr. Weaver's various appearances on NPR and other radio programming and feature topics about issues including women and the Catholic Church as well as Pope John Paul II's 1995 visit to the United States. The videotape also discusses women and Catholicism.
The Research notes, grants, and correspondence series contains research notes on a variety of topics, reports and other correspondence related to grants awarded to Dr. Weaver, as well as correspondence about the publication of her book Introduction to Christianity. Additionally, general correspondence regarding Dr. Weaver's administrative duties at IU, her professional involvement in a variety of organizations, and her publications is included in this series.
Separated Material
A file containing course evaluations was separated from the collection.
VHS Tape – "Is Catholic Feminism a Contradiction in Terms?," Prof. Mary Jo Weaver, 45:00, 1995 - Pulled and stored with 4111.9
Related Material
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IUScholarworks: http://scholarworks.iu.edu/
Acquisition Information
Accession 2010/100
Provenance
Gift of Mary Jo Weaver, November 2010.
Appraisal
Student evaluations of courses taught by Dr. Weaver were not found to have long term historical value and were removed from this collection.
Religion --Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington.; Weaver, Mary Jo -- Archives; Weaver, Mary Jo -- Correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Religious Studies -- Faculty -- Archives
- Biographical records, 1973-2010 (Box 1)
  - Awards, Degree, 1973-2006 (Box 1)
  - Conference and Lecture Brochures, 1978-1994 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vita, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Statements about Weaver's Activities Written by Others, 1982-2009 (Box 1)
  - Statements Written by Weaver about Her Teaching and Research, 1990-2005 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Summary Reports, 1975-2005 (Box 1)
  - Promotion, Tenure, and Salary Files[Restricted], 1978-1999 (Box 1)
  - Retirement Ceremony and Correspondence, 2005-2008 (Box 1)
  - Retirement Certificate, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Retirement Scrapbook, 2006 (Box 1)
- Publications and writings, 1972-2010; undated
  - Monographs, 1979-2009; undated
    - "Quest for Self/Quest for God" in The Bent World, Essays on Religion and Culture, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Letters from a "Modernist": The Letters of George Tyrrell to Wilfred Ward 1893-1980, Introduced and Annotated by Mary Jo Weaver, 1981 (Box 1)
    - "Thomas Merton and Flannery O'Conner: The Urgency of Vision" in Thomas Merton, Pilgrim in Process, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Introduction to Christianity, 1st Edition, 1984 (Box 1)
    - New Catholic Women, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Newman and the Modernists, Edited by Mary Jo Weaver, 1985 (Box 1)
    - "In Defense of Omnipotence: the Case Against Dialogue" in The Vatican and Homosexuality, 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Who is the Goddess and Where Does She Get Us?" in Neo-Paganism: A Feminist Search for Religious Alternatives, 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Pornography and the Religious Imagination" in For Adults Only: The Dilemma of Violent Pornography, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Introduction to Christianity, 2nd Edition, 1991 (Box 1)
    - "Widening the Sphere of Discourse: Reflections on the Feminist Perspective in Religious Studies" in Horizon on Catholic Feminist Theology, 1992 (Box 1)
    - "A Church We Long For: The Fundamentalist Challenge" in The Struggle Over the Past, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Springs of Water in a Dry Land, 1993 (Box 2)
    - "Still Feisty at Fifty: The Grailville Lay Apostate for Women", 1993 (Box 2)
    - "Feminists and Patriarchs in the Catholic Church: Orthodoxy and its Discontents" in Catholic Lives/Contemporary America, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Being Right: Conservative Catholics in America, Edited by Mary Jo Weaver and R. Scott Appleby (Box 2)
    - New Catholic Women, 1995 (Box 2)
    - "Cancer in the Body of Christ" in Women's Spirituality, 1996 (Box 2)
    - "Miriam Elder" in Carmel of the Resurrection 1922-1997 (Box 2)
    - Introduction to Christianity, 3rd Edition, 1998 (Box 2)
    - "American Catholics in the Twentieth Century" in Perspectives on American Religion and Culture, 1999 (Box 2)
    - What's Left? Liberal American Catholics, Edited by Mary Jo Weaver, 1999 (Box 2)
    - "Catholic Fundamentalism" in The Encyclopedia of Fundamentalism, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Cloister and Community: Life within a Carmelite Monastery, 2002 (Box 2)
    - "Lower Case Catholic" in Vatican II, 2003 (Box 2)
    - "Catholic Women Since Vatican II" in Women and Religion in North America – Draft, 2004 (Box 2)
    - "Feminists and Patriarchs in the Catholic Church: Orthodoxy and its Discontents" in Re-Imagining God for Today, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Introduction to Christianity, 4th Edition, 2009 (Box 2)
    - "The Roman Catholic Heritage" in the Encyclopedia of Religion in America, undated (Box 2)
    - "'Springs of Water in a Dry Land': A Process Model of Feminist Spirituality" in A Discipleship of Equals, undated (Box 2)
  - Subseries: Articles, 1975-2003; undated
    - "The Chinese Rites Case and Mission Theory", 1975 (Box 2)
    - "From Sin to Sanctity", 1976 (Box 2)
    - "Augustine and the Unending Quest", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Dante and the Baptized Imagination", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Enhancing and Evaluating the Discussion Section", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "The Feeling Intellect", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "The Gift of Christmas", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Master of the Images", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Master of the Images", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Leisure: A Way to Live the Gospel", 1978 (Box 2)
    - "Thomas Merton and Dorothy Day: From Theory to Practice, I", 1978 (Box 2)
    - "Thomas Merton and Dorothy Day: From Theory to Practice, II", 1978 (Box 2)
    - "Wilfred Ward, George Tyrrell and the Meanings of Modernism", 1978 (Box 2)
    - "A Bibliography of the Published Works of Wilfred Ward", 1979 (Box 2)
    - "Hellfire and Damnation: An Approach to Religion and Literature", 1979 (Box 2)
    - "Single Blessedness?", 1979 (Box 2)
    - "Thomas Merton and Flannery O'Connor: The Urgency of Vision", 1979 (Box 2)
    - "A Working Catalogue of the Ward Family Papers", 1979 (Box 2)
    - "George Tyrrell and the Joint Pastoral Letter", 1981 (Box 2)
    - "The North American Catholic Woman: Relationship to Self, Family, Institutions of Church and State", 1983 (Box 2)
    - "Single and Roman Catholic in the 80's", 1983 (Box 2)
    - "We Aren't Sisters", 1984 (Box 2)
    - "From Immigrants to Emigrants", 1985 (Box 2)
    - "Lay Signers Reflect on Statement", 1985 (Box 2)
    - "Lenten Journey 1985" (Box 2)
    - "Women and the Future of the Church", 1985 (Box 2)
    - "Feminist Perspectives and American Catholic History", 1986 (Box 2)
    - "A Church We Long for: The Fundamentalist Challenge", 1987 (Box 2)
    - "'Overcoming the Divisiveness of Babel': The Languages of Catholicity", 1987 (Box 2)
    - "A Discussion of Sallie McFague's Models of God: Introduction" in Religion and Intellectual Life, 1988 (Box 2)
    - "Eleanor Lahr Liberated", 1988 (Box 2)
    - "Who is the Goddess and Where Does She Get Us?", 1988 (Box 2)
    - "Widening the Sphere of Discourse: Reflections on the Feminist Perspective in Religious Studies", 1989 (Box 2)
    - "Empowered by an Alternative Tradition: Women's Options in an Uncongenial Church", 1990 (Box 2)
    - "John Tracy Ellis", 1993 (Box 2)
    - "The Most Adventurous of Nuns: Ursulines and the Future", 1993 (Box 2)
    - "Feminists and Patriarchs in the Catholic Church: Orthodoxy and Its Discontents", 1994 (Box 3)
    - "Being Right: Conservative American Catholics", 1996 (Box 3)
    - "Rooted Hearts/Playful Minds: Catholic Intellectual Life at Its Best", 1998 (Box 3)
    - "What's New", 1999 (Box 3)
    - "Conjectures of a Disenchanted Reader", 2003 (Box 3)
    - "Sheed and Ward", 2003 (Box 3)
    - "Celebrating Women Witnesses: Therese of Lisieux", undated (Box 3)
    - "Longing for Relationship: Leading a Spiritual Life in America at the End of the Millennium", undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 1972-2010; undated
    - Reviews Written By Weaver, 1972-2004 (Box 3)
    - Dissertation: πνεΰμα in Philo of Alexandria, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Letter or Editorial – "Sinless Fun" in U.S. Catholic, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Editorial – Commonweal, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Booklets or Pamphlets Written for St. Charles Borromeo Church, 1982-1985 (Box 3)
    - Reviews of Weaver's Publications, 1985-1996 (Box 3)
    - Weaver Predicts, 1985-2000 (Box 3)
    - Text Submitted for "Charter of the Rights of Catholics in the Church", 1986 (Box 3)
    - Response to Critiques of Her Book New Catholic Women, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Letter to the Editor – Commonweal, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Interview – Trekdom Blog, 2007 (Box 3)
    - Biography of Sister Elizabeth of the Sacred Heart, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Letter to the Editor – NCR, undated (Box 3)
    - Mary Jo Weaver's Book List: A Baker's Dozen, undated (Box 3)
- Presentations, 1974-2001; undated
  - "Sin", circa 1974, 1975 (Box 3)
  - "Catholics and the Bible," given at Monroe Public Library, 1976 (Box 3)
  - "Male God Language and Religious Alienation", 1980 (Box 3)
  - "Onward Christian Voters", 1980 (Box 3)
  - "Seduced and Abandoned: Jesus' Death and God's Suffering", 1980 (Box 3)
  - Sermons Given at St. Charles Borromeo Church, 1980-1985 (Box 3)
  - "Reformers, Radicals and Romantics", 1981 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Sermons, 1981-1982; undated (Box 3)
  - Notes and Drafts of Presentations, 1982-2001 (Box 3)
  - Presentations Given at St. Martin's Abbey in Oregon, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Sermons Given at St. Mark's Methodist Church in Bloomington, Indiana, 1983 (Box 3)
  - "We Will Not Comply! Civil and Ecclesiastical Disobedience of American Catholic Women", 1984 (Box 3)
  - "Aspects of Feminine Spirituality in the 19th Century: A Response", 1985 (Box 3)
  - "Ordination Reconsidered", 1986 (Box 3)
  - "Research and Writing of History", 1986 (Box 3)
  - "Response to Jung and Kern", 1990 (Box 3)
  - "Working on Being Right: Conservative Catholics Thirty Years After Council", 1995 (Box 3)
  - "What's Wrong with Being Right?", 1996 (Box 3)
  - "Who is This Woman? The Life of the Virgin in Textiles and Prints", 1998 (Box 3)
  - "Response to Schreiter Talk, 1999 (Box 3)
  - "What's Left is Us: Liberal Catholics at the End of the Millennium", 1999 (Box 3)
  - "Wisdom's Lure: the Power of Religious Studies", 1999 (Box 3)
  - "Teresa of Avila", 2001 (Box 3)
  - "The Creed," RCIA, undated (Box 3)
  - "Response to John Carmody", undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons Given at a Church in Mt. Vernon, Ohio, undated (Box 3)
  - "Star Trek and Religion: Theory and Practice", undated (Box 3)
- Teaching materials, 1972-2005; undated
  - Adult Education Classes, St. Charles, 1970s (Box 3)
  - "American Catholicism", 2000-2005 (Box 3)
  - "American Catholicism at Mid-Century", 2000 (Box 3)
  - "The Church and the Christian Life", 1974 (Box 3)
  - "Church as Pilgrim Church", 1975 (Box 3)
  - "Contemporary Religious Thought: The Pilgrimage from Sin to Sanctity", 1976 (Box 3)
  - "Feminist Critique of Western Religions", 1990-1993 (Box 3)
  - Graduate Seminars, 1977-1993; undated (Box 3)
  - "Hellfire and Damnation", 1977-1985 (Box 3)
  - "History of the Roman Catholic Church", undated (Box 3)
  - "Introduction to Christianity", 1993-2002; undated (Box 3)
  - "Introduction to Religion in the West", 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - "Modern American Catholicism", 1981-1997 (Box 3)
  - "Mystical Prayer and Western Spirituality", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Pilgrimage of the People of God", 1975 (Box 3)
  - Pontifical Josephinum Classes, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
  - "Religion and Literature", 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook Used in Women's Studies Courses[located in Box 4], undated (Box 3)
  - "Spiritual Autobiography", 2001 (Box 3)
  - "Star Trek and Religion," Folder 1 of 3, 1998-2005 (Box 3)
  - "Star Trek and Religion," Folder 2 of 3, 1998-2005 (Box 4)
  - "Star Trek and Religion," Folder 3 of 3, 1997-2000 (Box 4)
  - "Women and Religion", 1985-2000 (Box 4)
- Audio/Visual material, 1983-1996; undated
  - Audiotapes (Box 4)
    - Women and the Church 1983/1987, All Things Considered: NPR on Pope (Box 4)
      Online Streaming in Media Collections Online
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/8049gp331
      General
      Previous title: CU Cuti; NPR on Pope
    - "Let's Talk: Women Church – Its Struggle and Its Vision", 2/16/1986 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/q237j8996
      Previous Finding Aid Title: "Let's Talk: Women Church – Its Struggle and Its Vision": Rosemary R. Ruether, Mary Jo Weaver, Marjorie Tuite, Op, Moderator: Kay Ashe, Op
    - MJW on "New Catholic Women", 1986 September 27 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/2514p351m
    - 1991 Future of the American Church Conference: Roman Catholic Fundementalists: Expanding the Matrix of interpretation (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/s1785305j
      Previous title: 1991 Future of the American Church Conference 540 – "Roman Catholic Fundamentalists: Expanding the Matrix of Interpretation" – Dr. Mary Jo Weaver
    - Talk of the Nation: Briggs, Imesch and Weaver on Bishops' pastoral letter on women, 11/16/1992 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/g158c1122
      Previous title: Talk of the Nation: Briggs, LaCugna, Weaver – Bp's Pastoral
    - Talk of the Nation: Bishops' Pastoral Letter on Women/ Pope's Visit Aftermath, 11/16/1992; 8/16/1993 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/348500899
      Previous title: Talk of the Nation and
    - Fresh Air, 3/8/1993 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/r207v568v
    - Afternoon Magazine, WILL Radio: Catholics, 8/18/1993 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/3t9467737
      Previous title: Aftmag Will Radio: Catholics, Mary Jo Weaver, Scott Appleby, Msr. Steven Rohlfs
    - Weaver -- NPR-- Pope John Paul II Visit, 10/2/1995 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/6108vv12n
      Previous Title: Weaver – NPR – JPII Visit
    - Call to Action National conference: "What's right about, and Wrong With, Being Right?", 1996 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/4f16ck93c
      Previous title: 1996 Call to Action National Conference 96414-0830: Mary Jo Weaver – "What's Right About, and Wrong With, Being Right?"
    - Branches Radio Interview, 1/16/1996 (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/pv63gg71q
      Previous Title: Branches Radio
    - All Things Considered: Clergy & Women, undated (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/pk02cv09p
      Previous Title: All Things Considered #851027: Clergy and Women
    - Mary Jo Weaver Fresh Air Interview & Feature MASTER, undated (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/x920gd17t
      Previous Title: Fresh Air Master Interview and Feature
    - Mary Jo on NPR – Being Right, undated (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/0g354x873
    - Program 409: "15 Min. on Easter", undated (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/348500881
    - NPR Interview with Robert Siegel, undated (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/pc28b141x
      Previous title: NPR Siegel Interview
    - Terry Gross – Being Right, undated (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/7w62fr90w
    - Women In the Church Conference: A summary of Feminist Theological Developments, undated (Box 4)
      https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/h702qq36m
      Previous Title: Women in the Church Conference 86003-820: Dr. Mary Jo Weaver – A Summary of Feminist Theological Developments
  - VHS Tape – "Is Catholic Feminism a Contradiction in Terms?," Prof. Mary Jo Weaver, 45:00 (Pulled and stored with 4411.9), 1995 (Box 4)
- Research notes, grants, and correspondence, 1972-2006; undated
  - Correspondence – General, 1972-2002 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence – Publication of Introduction to Christianity, 1982-2006 (Box 4)
  - Grant Report – "Being Right: Conservative American Catholics", 1993-1996 (Box 4)
  - Grant Report – "Cooperation and the Community of Learning", 1981 (Box 4)
  - Grant Requests and Correspondence, 1981-1986 (Box 4)
  - Research Notes, 1973-2006; undated (Box 4)
    - Beth Johnson, undated (Box 4)
    - Dorothy Day, undated (Box 4)
    - Gabriel Daly: Roman Catholicism and Modernity, undated (Box 4)
    - General Research, 2006; undated (Box 4)
    - Homosexuality, 1987-1996 (Box 4)
    - Institutional Roman Catholicism, 1994-2005 (Box 4)
    - Irish Roman Catholics, 1973-1998 (Box 4)
    - Medieval Anti-Minority Violence, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Pierre Teilhard de Chardin, 2005; undated (Box 4)
    - Pope John XXIII, undated (Box 4)
    - Vatican II, undated (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook Used in Women's Studies Courses, undated (Box 4)
  - Restricted File (Box 4)